Inventory of the Louis Paul Lochner collection, 1933-1946
Hoover Institution Archives
- Economic news on the Soviet Union, 1945 February 2 (Box-folder 5: 25)
  Contains a German report.
- "Faces in the Night,", undated (Box-folder 5: 26)
  Contains photographic copies of artwork by German artist Erich Martin, an opponent of Nazism. Also includes a typescript copy of Martin's description of the work as well as a handwritten explanation of the significance of each photo written by H. Hartel, an American censor at Offenbach who contributed the contents of this file to Lochner.
- The Hartel collection of documents, 1945-1946, undated (Box-folder 5: 27)
  Various documents collected by H. Hartel consisting of election flyers for the Kassel district and election programs from a new party, the National-Democrats, and the Democratic Peoples' Party. It also contains a list of all the former Nazi Party members in Wiess-Baden; a speech by Dr. Wagembach of Giessen; a speech by the Social-Democratic leader for Greater Hesse, Wilhelm Knowthe; and a pamphlet, "Questions and Answers," by Anton Ackermann on the alleged necessity for a union of the Communists and Social-Democrats. Finally, it contains excerpts from letters by refugees that went through the censorship as well as a few poems written under the impact of expulsion.
- Damm, Paul correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 6: 1)
- Sudeten material, 1946 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  Documents in German related to the feeding of the Germans, especially Catholics, ejected from the Sudeten area of Czechoslovakia.
- Copy of letter by the sub-prefect of the French Zone at Freiburg, 1946 June 18 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  Informs all the German political parties that in election speeches there must be no mention of a German central government, of the internationization of the Ruhr and Rhineland, and of the economic junction of the Saar to France.
- Denazification of Material--Austria, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  A collection of Austrian denazification laws supplied by the principal denazification officer for American Military Government in Austria, Mr. M. Wallach.
- Denazification material--Germany, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  Contains government orders, posters, graphs, a British questionnaire (Fragebogen), directives, a registration blank (Meldebogen), and two monthly denazification reports. Also included is a "Note on Denazification in the Hansestadt Hamburg," a copy of a letter by Franz Karl Maier charging the Prime Minister of Wuerttemberg-Baden with collaborating with the Nazis, a request for the denazification minister, a Dr. Kamm, to rule on his objections to certain phases of denazification, and a plan for changing the Law for Liberation from National Socialism and Militarism.
- Political pamphlets and documents from Wurttemberg-Baden, circa 1936 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  Handbills and appeals issued during the 1936 election campaigns.
- Program and other details of the First Convention of the Federation of Trade Unions of Wurttemberg-Baden, 1946 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  This convention was held August 30-September 1 of 1946 at Kornwestheim near Stuttgart.
- Gestapo document, 1939 February 11 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  Contains an indictment against a man from Stuttgart named Richard Schmid, who was accused of complicity in a treasonable plot.
- "Requests of the Laenderrat to Military Government,", 1946 Decmber 3 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  A report detailing the decisions and results of the Laenderrat meeting in Stuttgart.
- The situation in Stuttgart, 1946-1947, undated (Box-folder 6: 10)
  Contains documents indicating the problems of the capital of Wurttemberg-Baden, Stuttgart.
- Documents regarding the American Zone, undated (Box-folder 6: 11)
  Contains a document explaining the Regional Government Coordinating Office in the American Zone, as well as biographical material concerning various German officials in the American Zone.
- Refugee camp overcrowding, 1946 October 19 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  Contains a report by a health officer to the American military in Wurttemberg-Baden, indicating an increase in various epidemics, especially diphtheria.
- Goodwill Youth Club, Stuttgart, 1946 (Box-folder 6: 13)
  A copy of the by-laws of a club for young Germans and Americans, formed under American auspices. In German.
- Writings of Emmy Dorthea Dill, 1947 (Box-folder 6: 14)
  Contains various writings in English and German by Dill, who described herself as an authoress of Bad Durkeim in the French Zone.
- Law for making farmland available for settlement in the American Zone, 1946 August 13 (Box-folder 6: 15)
  In German.
- Der Wirtschaft Spiegel (Economic Mirror), 1946-1947 (Box-folder 6: 16)
  Two copies of the issue for December-January, 1946-47.
- Typescript by A. von Megulnoff, Berlin, undated (Box-folder 6: 17)
  Typescript titled "Gefahr für den Welfrieden" (Danger to World Peace) describing an antibolshevik Russian living in exile in Berlin.
- "Die Existenzmoglichkeit Deutschlands in Beziehung zur Festlegung seiner Grenzen" (The Possibilities for Existence for Germany as Related to the Fixation of Her Boundaries), undated (Box-folder 6: 18)
  Two copies of a document written by Dr. Grimm, former executive director of the Chamber of Commerce of Hirschberg, Silesia. Dr. Grimm seeks to prove that the eastern boundaries of Germany as then interpreted by Russia and Poland will mean a catastrophe. Contributed by A. von Megulnoff.
- "Zer Frage der Bodenreform,", undated (Box-folder 6: 19)
  Describes developments in the Russian Zone concerning land reform, provisioning of greater Berlin, and the deportation of German skilled workers. Contributed by Rev. Jochen Wilde, a Lutheran pastor who opposed Hitler and communism.
- Helmuth Wissmann collection, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 7: 1)
- Photostat of typical Russian Secret Service (NKVD) passport, circa 1946 (Box-folder 7: 2)
- Major Merle A. Potter collection, 1946 (Box-folder 7: 3)
- Sudeten documents, 1941-1945, undated (Box-folder 7: 4)
- Proceedings of the Social Democratic Party Convention at Hanover, 1946 May 8-11 (Box-folder 7: 5)
- Documents from the Hohenzollern Archives, 1924-1946 (Box-folder 7: 6)
- Papers submitted by Prince Louis Ferdinand of Prussia, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 7: 7)
- Otto Nuschke papers, 1932-1934 (Box-folder 7: 8)
- Article by Max Schnitzer on the Hoover War Library, undated (Box-folder 7: 9)
- Die Ernaehrung des Deutschen Volkes (The Nutrition of the German People) by Dr. Wilhelm Ziegelmayer, 1947 (Box-folder 7: 10-12)
- "Das Demokratische Deutschland,", 1945 (Box-folder 8: 1)
- Kurt Heyd collection, 1933-1945, undated (Box-folder 8: 2)
- Economic data concerning Germany, 1941-1947 (Box-folder 8: 3)
- Troop information and education, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 8: 4-7)
- Karl Brammer, "So lebten sie: 700 Milliarden Schulden,", 1946 (Box-folder 9: 1)
- Rudolf Diels, "Die Amfänge der Gestapo,", 1946 (Box-folder 9: 2)
- Hans Karl Ernst Ludwig Keller, 1946, undated (Box-folder 9: 3)
  Contains two typescripts: "Die Akademie für die Rechte der Völker und die Freiheit der Wissenschaft" and "The History of the Academy for the Rights of Nations."
- Walther F. Kleffel, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  Contains four typescripts: "Zeitliches," "Die grosse Enttäuschung," "Der Bannstrahl," and "Auf falschen Wegen."
- Clemens Lammers, "Reichsverband der Deutschen Industrie und Machtergreifung,", 1946 (Box-folder 9: 5)
- Cornelia and Uta Maass, letter to Adolf Hitler, 1944 October 10 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  A plea for Hermann Maass who was sentenced to death for his part in the attempt on Hitler's life at Potsdam.
- Eva Maass, letter to Otto Thierack, Minister of Justice, 1944 October 21 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  Sent on behalf of Hermann Maass who was sentenced to death for his part in the attempt on Hitler's life at Potsdam.
- Hermann Maass, letter to his wife, 1944 August 12-13 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  Written shortly before Maass' execution.
- Kurt Mair, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 9: 9-11)
  Contains "Seven Documents Relating to the Operation of the Interradio A. G.," a letter addressed to General Mark Clark requesting the speedy investigation of internees in Walchsee, and "Teilabschrift aus Briefen an österreichische Regierungsmitglieder und an österreichische Nationalräte."
- Hansjörg Maurer, 1936-1947 (Box-folder 10: 1-3)
  Contains "Mein Tagebuch," "Meine politischen Tagebuch-Blätter," and "Meine Confessio Vitae" (My Confession of My Life)."
- Horst Pelskmann, "Plaidoyer fuer die 'SS' Schutzstaffel der NSDAP gehalten vor dem Internationalen Militaergerichtshof, Nürnberg,", 1946 (Box-folder 10: 4)
- Ernst Poensgen, "Hitler und die Ruhrindustriellen: ein Rückblick,", circa 1945 (Box-folder 10: 5)
- Winifred Wagner's defense, circa 1946 (Box-folder 10: 6)
- Albert Wolf, "Der Weg in den Abgrund" (The Road into the Abyss), circa 1946 (Box-folder 10: 7)